[SPEAKER_01]: How important is thinking in practice?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's not like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I say it's not optional because I know that, you know, people, especially when it comes to the Buddhist practice or even practice of meditation, they think, oh, you just need to stop thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you fail... they fail to understand that that's a contradiction in terms, because that's another thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Our stop thinking is a thought that just tries to deny itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you go around thinking that you're abstaining from thinking by thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's impossible to not think.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only in second jhāna, the thoughts would subside.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not to say that you stopped thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just means you refined your... your... your... your context and your composure,
[SPEAKER_00]: To the extent that even the movement of the thoughts now is too coarse.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like you should stop thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about you must learn how to think skillfully, to the point of entering the first jhāna, which is the the purest way of thinking you can have, thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that, in itself, is enough for Arahantship.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what about wisdom?
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people think that wisdom is... or understanding comes from feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, like the intuitive wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's another contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's intuitive, means it's felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's felt, means it's not understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the understanding...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you develop understanding, you will be free from feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Arahant, who has developed full understanding of the experience as a whole, he doesn't feel anything as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why he's cooled down.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a person who feels doesn't understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the extent you feel, to that extent you're lacking understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's that's what wisdom is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't mean understanding in psychological manner, or this is what's happening to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean understanding the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what wisdom is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wisdom means perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: We covered that in other talks, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean intelligence, doesn't mean... but means perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't have, oh, intuitive perspective that I can't quite put in the words.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just you mystifying your own feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, trying to understand something, a problem, by feeling... By feeling what?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, I've got a problem, so if I feel the problem, then feeling it, experiencing it, through feeling, I will understand it and become wise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just through mere feeling it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, feeling it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then we wouldn't need the whole dhamma and the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: If all you need to do is feel it, to be free from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would the Buddha spend 40 years of teaching how to free yourself from feeling and suffering involved with it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you choose to
[SPEAKER_00]: Feel it more or not, the problem is there first.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a problem in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact that you're liable to a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if there is no problem, as the Buddha said, you recognize.
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I a subject to sickness, aging, death, misfortune, loss?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now I'm not sick, dying or losing anything, but I am subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, I am liable to these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will have to happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't actually want to wait for that problem to become acute.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to recognize it that even without the problem, you are within that liability to a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what dukkha is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha wasn't sick and dying when he left the home.
[SPEAKER_00]: He saw other people being sick and dying and then he said, oh, I'm...
[SPEAKER_00]: I cannot escape this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will... this will have to affect me at some point in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the concern that he talks about.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you wait for the problem to be affecting you,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, to feel it, that's just you trying to basically wiggle your way out of it, sort of manage it, psychologize it, deal with it, once it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how to get wisdom?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you get wisdom from... Well, you get wisdom by developing a perspective on your own situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That perspective is just what I described.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not about
[SPEAKER_00]: When I get a problem, I will do this, and then I will do that, and then I will feel this.
[SPEAKER_00]: All that can be in place, whatever, but you want to extend that perspective and realize, can I not have any problem in the future?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are there things in me that I'm not abandoning, because of which problems can land on me, suffering can affect me?
[SPEAKER_00]: So you actually... that's what wisdom is, preemptively developing perspective to basically leave the domain where the problems arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abandon suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, dukkha does not mean suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means dis-ease.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means that uneasiness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you are uneasy when you don't have any problem, but when you recognize that in a day or two, there's going to be a big problem coming your way.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know what specific problem it will be, but you know it will have to arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, you get anxious.
[SPEAKER_00]: You get uneasy.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, but there is no problem, specifically, that you have to feel and get in touch with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, there is a problem, because you recognize that liability to a problem is a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you can try and feel it all you want, it will not uproot your liability.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only developing that perspective further and abandoning passion in regard to it, is what develops that wisdom, that uproots the liability to it.